<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>

<!--
 ***************************************************
 Please see license.xml for this document's license.
 ***************************************************
-->

<chapter id="cha.concept.overview" xml:base="concept_overview.xml">
 <chapterinfo>
  <date><?dbtimestamp?></date>
  <releaseinfo>First Draft</releaseinfo>
  <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>
  <releaseinfo>$Date: 2007-02-22 17:21:45 +0100 (Thu, 22 Feb 2007) $</releaseinfo>
  <authorgroup>
   <author>
    <firstname>Frank</firstname>
    <surname>Sundermeyer</surname>
   </author>
  </authorgroup>
  <keywordset>
   <keyword>Build Service</keyword>
  </keywordset>
 </chapterinfo>
 <title>Overview</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   The openSUSE Build Service is an open and complete distribution development
   platform. It supplies the infrastructure for the development of the openSUSE
   distribution. Furthermore it provides software developers with a tool to
   compile, release and publish their software for different Linux
   distributions and makes it available to the broad user audience. The
   openSUSE Build Service also provide means to create custom Linux
   distributions for various hardware architectures.
  </para>
 </abstract>
 <sect1 id="sec.concept.overview.features">
  <title>Features</title>
  <para>
   Although the Build Service is primarily a platform for developers, it also
   offers functionality for Linux users and even for distributors. The Build
   Service is currently work in progress. Future versions will, for instance,
   have a trust management for users and projects. It is also planned to offer
   the build of flavors of distributions, such as openSUSE for XEN, Live DVDs,
   and others. More information on planned features are availabe at <ulink
    url="http://en.opensuse.org/Build_Service/Future_Ideas"/> and <ulink
    url="http://en.opensuse.org/Build_Service/Roadmap"/>.
  </para>
  <sect2 id="sec.concept.overview.features.developers">
   <title>Features for Developers</title>
   <para>
    A developer who wants to make his software available for as much people as
    possible, faces three major problems:  
   </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>The software should run on most distributions.</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>
      The software should run on different versions of distributions.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>The software should run on most hardware platforms.</para>
    </listitem>    
   </itemizedlist>
   <para>
    It is almost impossible to meet these challenges for a regular developer.
    He not only would have to have all target distributions and versions
    installed, he would also have to have access all hardware platforms the
    software should be available for.
   </para>
   <para>
    The Build Service solves these issues. Apart from openSUSE, it supports
    other popular Linux distributions (like Fedora, Debian, Ubuntu, and others)
    as well as several hardware platforms (i386, x86-64, and PPC [planned]).  
   </para>
   <para>
    Another major issue are package dependencies. Most software depends on
    other software packages (such as libraries, for instance). The Build
    Service automatically resolves these dependencies. Whatsmore, it even
    triggers an automatic package rebuild once a depending package has been
    updated. Therefore it is no longer necessary to keep track of package
    changes on all target distributions.
   </para>
   <para>
    When maintaining software depending on other projects such as KDE or GNOME,
    for instance, it is possible to link the package to these projects. This
    ensures that a rebuild is triggered when the project it is linked to is
    also rebuilded.
   </para>
   <para>
    Each software project on the Build Service is hosted in a workspace called
    project. Each project can have sub-projects and different projects can be
    linked to each other.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.concept.overview.features.user">
   <title>Features for Users</title>
   <para>
    Each project that is hosted on the Build Service is available for
    download and installation via repositories of various formats (apt, rpm-md
    [<quote>Yum</quote>], SUSE legacy). Using these repositories users can
    easily get the latest version of their favorite software. Since
    dependencies are automatically resolved, it is even possible to always
    update to the latest versions of large projects such as KDE or GNOME.
   </para>
   <para>
    Since the Build Service not only hosts current distributions, it also
    provides updates for older versions. Theoretically it is also possible to
    provide security updates for distributions no longer maintained.
   </para>
   <para>
    The (planned) trust management where users rate projects and project
    owners, helps to find out about the popularity of a certain project. If a
    user likes a certain project, he can promote it by voting for it.
   </para>
  </sect2>
  <sect2 id="sec.concept.overview.features.distributors">
   <title>Features for Distributors</title>
   <para>
    The Build Service is able to create complete distributions or modified
    images easily to be used in different ways. A first version of KIWI to
    create images for booting via network or to be used as Xen or VMware image
    has been released. See <xref linkend="cha.kiwi"/> for more information.
   </para>
  </sect2>
 </sect1>
</chapter>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
coding:utf-8
mode:xml
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
End:
-->
