<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>

<!--
 ***************************************************
 Please see license.xml for this document's license.
 ***************************************************
-->

<sect1 id="sec.kiwi.create" xml:base="kiwi_create.xml">
  <title>Creating Operating System Images</title>
  <para>To create an operating system image with KIWI, you must first create a <emphasis>system
      image description</emphasis>. This description is a directory containing at least one file
    named <filename>config.xml</filename>. Among other things,.the <filename>config.xml</filename>
    file lists the packages and patterns used to make your image, the source repositories the data
    should be obtained from, and the image types that can be generated from this description (see <xref linkend="sec.kiwi.description"/> for more information).</para>
  <para>You can use an existing system image description as a template. An image description is
    normally provided as an architecture-independent package. For your reference, you can download
      <filename>kiwi-desc-livesystem</filename> from <ulink
      url="http://download.opensuse.org/repositories/openSUSE:/Tools"/>. This package contains
    descriptions for openSUSE live systems, which can serve as a basis for other image types.</para>
  <para>The process of creating an image starts with a <command>prepare</command> command, which
    requires at least the path to your system image description and an optional destination
    directory as arguments.</para>

  <screen>kiwi --prepare /path_to_description --root /tmp/myroot</screen>

  <para>The result of this step is an operating system which has its root directory below the given
    destination directory (<filename>/tmp/myroot</filename> in this example). After this step, the
    new root directory serves as the data source for creating the requested operating system image.
    This step is called the <emphasis>create</emphasis> step, and requires, at minimum, the path to
    your previously created new root environment and a destination directory for the image files.</para>

  <screen>kiwi --create /tmp/myroot --destdir /tmp/myimages</screen>

  <para>The destination directory (<filename>/tmp/myimages</filename> in this example) must exist
    before you run the command. KIWI stores all files for the requested image type below this
    directory. KIWI lets you specify <emphasis>defaultroot</emphasis> and
      <emphasis>defaultdestination</emphasis> attributes as part of <filename>config.xml</filename>.
    If these attributes are present, and the <emphasis>--root</emphasis> and/or
    <emphasis>--destdir</emphasis> options are not specified, the information from the
      <emphasis>default</emphasis> attributes is used.</para>
  <para>In addition to creating your system image, KIWI also provides a subsystem for image
    deployment. Each system image needs to be activated in some manner. For example, the system
    image for a network client must be downloaded from a server, installed, and a disk must be
    partitioned. The steps that must be performed before a system image is activated are done in the
    so called <emphasis>boot image</emphasis>. KIWI provides boot images for all of its supported
    image types. KIWI creates them automatically when the <command>create</command> command is run.</para>
  <para>The KIWI boot images are special initrd images that contain the image type they should
    activate. The boot images are implemented as normal KIWI image descriptions, and are stored in a
    subdirectory below <filename>/usr/share/kiwi/image</filename>. The subdirectories use the naming
    scheme <replaceable>type</replaceable>boot. For example, the boot images for network images are
    stored in the directory <filename>netboot/</filename>, and the boot images for virtual disk
    images are stored in <filename>vmxboot/</filename>. Boot images should not require any
    modifications by the user. For more information on boot images, see <xref
      linkend="sec.kiwi.description.config"/>.</para>
</sect1>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
coding:utf-8
mode:xml
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
End:
-->
