<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>

<!--
 ***************************************************
 Please see license.xml for this document's license.
 ***************************************************
-->

<sect1 id="sec.project_structure.projects">
 <title>Projects</title>
 <abstract>
  <para>
   A project is a collection of software packages maintained by a team.  You
   can grant different rights to the team members.  Users can subscribe to such
   a project and use it as an installation source to enhance their installed
   openSUSE system.
  </para>
 </abstract>

 <sect2 id="sec.project_structure.projects.bs">
  <title>The openSUSE Build Service as a Project Repository</title>
  <para>
   The openSUSE Build Service at <ulink url="http://build.opensuse.org/" /> is
   a platform suitable to prepare software collections for installation on a
   range of systems.  These software collections are organized as projects and
   thus you can consider the Build Service as a repository of software
   projects.
  </para>


  <remark condition="clarity">
   2007-08-28 - fs:
   The following paragraph needs to be revised. The definition of a normal
   project could be more precise.
  </remark>
  <para>Inside the Build Service a subtle distinction exists between so called
   "home projects" and normal projects.  While every maintainer owns a generic
   "home project" at
   <filename>http://build.opensuse.org/project/show?project=home:<replaceable>MAINTAINER</replaceable></filename>, 
   where he can work on software packages he is interested in, a normal
   project is meant to be a collection of packages belonging together to form
   a somehow connected or thematically consistent package set, ranging from
   single program projects such as <systemitem>mozilla</systemitem> or
   <systemitem>screen</systemitem> to broader collections such as
   <systemitem>ruby</systemitem>, <systemitem>GNOME:STABLE</systemitem>,
   <systemitem>KDE:KDE4</systemitem>, or even
   <systemitem>openSUSE:Factory</systemitem>.
  </para>

 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.project_structure.projects.components">
  <title>Project Components</title>

  <para>A project is maintained by one or more maintainers, who are allowed to
  add or remove maintainers and manage projects.  You manage projects by adding
  or removing either packages or build repositories, for which the packages are
  meant to be built.  Build repositories often are base distributions such as
  <systemitem>openSUSE 10.2</systemitem>, <systemitem>openSUSE
  Factory</systemitem> (the development tree of openSUSE) plus optional
  enhancements.
</para>

  <para>Maintainers can also assign "tags" to a project.  Consider "tags" als
  labels, that help users to find projects belonging together in certain ways.
</para>

  <para>Build Service users (end users) can watch projects and rate 
  them<!--who are not involved in the package build process-->.
</para>

 </sect2>
</sect1>

<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
coding:utf-8
mode:xml
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
End:
-->
