<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE sect1 PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.4//EN"
  "http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.4/docbookx.dtd"
[
 <!ENTITY % entities SYSTEM "entity-decl.ent">
 %entities;
]>

<!--
 ***************************************************
 Please see license.xml for this document's license.
 ***************************************************
-->

<sect1 id="sec.webclient.project" xml:base="webclient_example.xml">
 <title>Setting up a Project with the Web Interface</title>
 <abstract>
  <para> Example project <remark>TODO: Enhance abstract</remark></para>
 </abstract>
 <sect2 id="sec.webclient.project.prerequisites">
  <title>Prerequisites</title>
  <para>Before you use the &bs; check the following prerequisites:</para>
  <remark>Is the list too simple? Maybe we can add some more valuable points here.</remark>
  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>You have a buildservice account. This is the same as your Wiki or Bugzilla account. If you
     do not have one, you can register by clicking <guimenu>Login</guimenu> from the main page of
     the <ulink url="http://build.opensuse.org" /> page and create one.</para>
    <remark>http://en.opensuse.org/Build_Service_Tutorial#Requirements</remark>
    <remark>TODO: Any recommendations for a login name?</remark>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>You should have a general understanding about how to create RPM packages or similiar
     systems.</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>You need some additional RPM packages for the <command>osc</command> command line
    client.</para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>  
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.webclient.project.gettingstarted">
  <title>Getting Started</title>
  <para>There are two ways of creating RPM packages:</para>
  <itemizedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>the web client which is described in this chapter</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>the commandline utility <command>osc</command> (see <remark>FIXME: Add
     link</remark>)</para>
   </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  <para>The overall picture of a project which is created on &bs; (be it with the web client or
   through command line):</para>

  <orderedlist>
   <listitem>
    <para>You login first into <ulink url=" http://build.opensuse.org" /></para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>You create your packages and upload them</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>You add for which distribution your package should be build</para>
   </listitem>
   <listitem>
    <para>You let your package build</para>
   </listitem>
  </orderedlist>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.webclient.project.login">
  <title>Login</title>
  <remark>INFO: From http://en.opensuse.org/Build_Service_Tutorial#Step_One_-_Login</remark>
  <para>To login into the &bs; proceed as follows:</para>

  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>Open the URL <ulink url="http://build.opensuse.org" /></para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Click on <guilabel>Login</guilabel> or enter your username and password in the upper left
     corner</para>
   </step>
  </procedure>

  <para>After a successful login you see the welcome page. In the upper right corner
   you see that you are logged in as your username. You can easily move to
   your <guilabel>Watched Projects</guilabel>, your <guilabel>Home
    Project</guilabel> or you can <guilabel>Logout</guilabel>.</para>

 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.webclient.project.creating">
  <title>Creating and Uploading Your Packages</title>
  <para>Although it is not necessary to create a package in your home project it is a good start to
   do so. Your home project is a good place to test and play around with your
   packages. In your home project you can familiarize with the Build Server
   and you do not disturb others if errors occur.</para>
  <para>To create a new package do the following:</para>
  <procedure>
   <step>
    <para>Login as described in <xref linkend="sec.webclient.project.login" />.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Click at <guilabel>Home Project</guilabel>. The webpage of your home project shows
    up.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Click at <guilabel>Add Package</guilabel>.</para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Fill out the text input fields with useful information: <guilabel>Name</guilabel> will go
     into the RPM package name, <guilabel>Title</guilabel> is the package summary, and
      <guilabel>Description</guilabel> information is a short abstract about the package.</para>
    <note>
     <title>Think About the Name Twice</title>
     <para>You can edit the above information later, but not the name. If you decide your
      package should reside under a different name, you can not rename it. At the moment it is only
      possible to delete this package and recreate it with a different name.</para>
    </note>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Proceed with <guibutton>Save changes</guibutton>. </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Upload the source code and the SPEC file of your package with <guilabel>Add
     File</guilabel>. </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <para>You have created a package and uploaded the sources. The next step deals with how to build a
   package for a certain distribution.</para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.webclient.project.adding">
  <title>Adding Distribution</title>
  <para>After you have created the package, it is now time to create a distribution. A distribution
   can be almost any SUSE version Factory (the latest and greatest current build) and even other
   work from Debian, Ubuntu or RedHat. A distribution is not only a <quote>flavor</quote> of Linux
   or Windows, it is also targeted to a architecture (x86, x86_64, &hellip;).</para>
  <para>To add a distribution to your package click on <guilabel>Add Repository</guilabel> and
   choose from the available distributions and architectures.</para>
  <para>After this step you have created a package, added the platform and architecture and now you
   can build your package with the next step.</para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.webclient.project.building">
  <title>Building the Package</title>
  <para>Generally, after you have uploaded your source files and SPEC file your package is scheduled
   for building. In other words, if everything is complete the build process starts automatically.</para>
  <para>You can trigger a build manually by clicking <guilabel>Trigger Rebuild</guilabel>.</para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.webclient.project.log">
  <title>Checking the Result</title>
  <para>After your build is finished you can view the results by clicking on <guilabel>Build
   Log</guilabel>. Sometimes the SPEC file contains syntax errors, or the build process can not
   resolve a dependency or you added more files to the RPM package than it is allowed&mdash;the
   log file tells you about this. If you find an error, find more information in the <remark>FIXME:
    Add troubleshooting link</remark></para>
 </sect2>

 <sect2 id="sec.webclient.project.moreinfo">
  <title>For More Information</title>
  <para>If you need help there are some resources that are useful:</para>
  <variablelist>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <ulink url="http://lists.opensuse.org/archive/opensuse-buildservice/">opensuse-buildservice
      Mailinglist</ulink>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>The buildservice mailinglist can be seeked for help and advice. However, decisions on
      which patches to apply, what compiler flags to use, etc. are ultimately up to you.</para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/SUSE_Build_Tutorial">SUSE Build Tutorial</ulink>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>Explains how to build packages that conforms the SUSE policy.</para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <ulink url="http://en.opensuse.org/Build_Service/Tips_and_Tricks">Tips and Tricks</ulink>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>Some collections with tips and tricks to work with the &bs;.</para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
   <varlistentry>
    <term>
     <ulink url="irc://irc.freenode.net/openSUSE-buildservice">#openSUSE-buildservice</ulink>
    </term>
    <listitem>
     <para>Some developers hang around in the IRC channel on freenode.</para>
    </listitem>
   </varlistentry>
  </variablelist>

 </sect2>

</sect1>
<!-- Keep this comment at the end of the file
Local variables:
coding:utf-8
mode:xml
sgml-indent-step:1
sgml-omittag:nil
sgml-shorttag:nil
End:
-->
